<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book id="groimp-manual">
	<title>GroIMP User Manual</title>
	<bookinfo>
		<title>GroIMP User Manual</title>
		<pubdate>2006</pubdate>
		<copyright>
			<year>2007</year>
<holder>Lehrstuhl Grafische Systeme,
Brandenburgische Technische Universität Cottbus</holder>
		</copyright>
		<legalnotice>
<para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2 or any later
version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections,
no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is
included in the section entitled "GNU Free Documentation License".</para>
		</legalnotice>
	</bookinfo>
	<preface>
		<title>Preface</title>
		<para>Dear user of GroIMP,</para>
		<para>this is the user manual of GroIMP, the GROGRA-related
Interactive Modelling Platform. GroIMP is OSI certified open source software
and available at the web page <ulink
url="http://www.grogra.de/">www.grogra.de</ulink>. Currently, the GroIMP
software is in a BETA state, which means that malfunctions may occur, though
the software has been tested in-depth. The latest news can be found at the web
page.</para>

		<para>GroIMP arose out of academic research in the field of
plant modelling, mainly carried out by the <ulink
url="http://www-gs.informatik.tu-cottbus.de/">Chair for Practical Computer
Science / Graphics Systems</ulink> at the Brandenburg University of Technology
Cottbus (Germany) and the <ulink
url="http://fbi.forst.uni-goettingen.de/">Plant Modelling Group</ulink> at the
Institute of Forest Biometry and Informatics at the University of Göttingen
(Germany). During research, techniques of rule-based plant-modelling were
developed and refined, and quickly it became clear that these rather abstract
techniques have to be accompanied by a smart, interactive and user-friendly
software platform with an up-to-date graphical user interface. The result of
the effort of bringing together elaborated rule-based modelling and
user-friendly, interactive software is GroIMP and its various plug-ins, which
extend GroIMP with additional functionality.</para>
<para>In the current version, GroIMP supports 3D modelling with OpenGL-based rendering,
including various forms of NURBS
surfaces, rule-based modelling using Lindenmayer systems and rule-based
modelling using Relational Growth Grammars (RGG) expressed in the programming
language XL. It also contains a 2D interface for
visualization and modification of network-like structures.</para><para>As
GroIMP is open source software, you are invited to contribute to this
software. Have a look at the web page to get the latest news and source
code!</para><para>In its current state, this user manual is by far not
complete. It explains some basics of how to work with GroIMP's user interface,
more detailed documentation will be published later.</para><para>We wish you
much fun and success with GroIMP.</para><para>The GroIMP development
team</para>

	</preface>
	<chapter>
		<title>Installation</title>
		<section><title>System Requirements</title><para>GroIMP is
written in Java. Thus,  it should follow Java's WORA-principle (Write Once, Run
Anywhere) and should run on every Java-capable platform. GroIMP has been tested
successfully on Unix and  Windows platforms.</para><para>GroIMP 0.9.3 requires
the installation of a  Java runtime environment of version 1.4 or later. Both
can  be obtained from Sun at <ulink
url="http://java.sun.com/">java.sun.com</ulink>.</para><para>For a reasonably
performant runtime behaviour, at least 256 MB RAM and a 1 GHz processor are
recommended.</para></section><section><title>Installation of the Binary
Distribution</title><para>The binary distribution of GroIMP is available at the
web page <ulink url="http://www.grogra.de/">www.grogra.de</ulink> as a
zip-file. The zip-file contains all necessary GroIMP files, they have to be
extracted into an installation directory of your choice by a common zip
programme. The directory structure of the zip-file has to be preserved, check
that your zip programme is set up accordingly (and does not extract all files
into one  and the same directory).</para><para>After extraction of the
zip-file, the following files, among others, are present in the installation
directory:
</para><variablelist><varlistentry><term><filename>README</filename></term>
<listitem><para>This
plain text file contains additional information about the GroIMP
distribution. Read it
carefully.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><filename>INSTALL</filename></term><listitem><para>This
plain text file contains  instructions for the installation of the GroIMP
distribution, legal notices and other information. Read it carefully. If you
have troubles with the installation procedure described in this manual, consult
the file <filename>INSTALL</filename> for a
solution.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><filename>plugins</filename></term><listitem><para>This
directory contains all the plugins that are part of the binary distribution of
GroIMP.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><filename>core.jar</filename></term><listitem><para>This
file is an executable java archive and the entry-point for the Java runtime
environment to start the GroIMP application.
See <xref linkend="s-running"/>.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist></section>

<section id="s-running"><title>Running GroIMP</title>

<section><title>From the Command Line</title>

<para>The file <filename>core.jar</filename> in your installation directory of
GroIMP's binary distribution is the entry-point for starting GroIMP. Running
GroIMP from the command line is easy:<blockquote>
<para><prompt>&gt;</prompt> <command>java -jar path/to/core.jar</command> </para>
</blockquote>Of course, <filename>path/to/core.jar</filename> has to be
replaced by the actual path to the file <filename>core.jar</filename>. E.g.,
if, on a Unix system, the installation directory is
<filename>/usr/lib/groimp</filename>, the command would be<blockquote>
<para><prompt>&gt;</prompt> <command>java -jar /usr/lib/groimp/core.jar</command> </para>
</blockquote>or, on a Windows system with installation directory
<filename>C:\Program Files\GroIMP</filename>,<blockquote>
<para><prompt>&gt;</prompt> <command>java -jar "C:\Program Files\GroIMP\core.jar"</command> </para></blockquote></para></section>

<section><title>From Your System's File Browser</title>

<para>Because
	  <filename>core.jar</filename> is an executable java archive, it is
	  possible to start GroIMP just by (double-)clicking on the file in
	  your system's file browser as you would do it with a usual executable
	  file. This requires a suitable setup of your file browser, see the
	  documentation of the browser and your Java installation if it does
	  not already work.</para></section><section><title>From a Menu Entry
	  of Your Desktop</title><para>You can set up your desktop to show a
	  menu entry for GroIMP. How this is done depends on your
	  system. Usually your system provides a menu editor where you can
	  create a new menu entry and
	  specifiy the command to be executed when the entry is
activated. Choose the command as you would do on command
line.</para></section><section><title>Java Options</title><para>The
<command>java</command> command has several options which influence the runtime
behaviour, see the documentation of your Java installation. These options have
to be specified before the <option>-jar</option> option. E.g., for the Java
runtime environment of Sun, the option <option>-Xmx</option> specifies the
maximum amount of heap memory size that should be allocated.
The default value of this option may be much smaller than your installed
main memory size. In this case GroIMP cannot benefit from your memory
until you specify the <option>-Xmx</option> option as in<blockquote>
<para><prompt>&gt;</prompt> <command>java -Xmx400m -jar path/to/core.jar</command> </para>
</blockquote>which allows a maximum heap memory allocation of
400 MB. If you encounter
<classname>OutOfMemoryError</classname>s when running GroIMP,
you have to specify this option with a larger
value.</para></section></section>

<section id="s-imageio"><title>Installation of Plugins for the Java Image I/O
Framework</title>

<para>GroIMP requires only a Java runtime environment in order to run. However,
the capabilities of some parts of the Java runtime environment can be extended
by the installation of additional plugins. GroIMP makes use of the Java Image
I/O Framework which provides such a pluggable architecture: The user may
install plugins which add support for an image file format to the Java Image
I/O Framework. If the standard installation of the Java runtime environment
does not support an image file format you need, please consult the
<ulink url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/docs/guide/imageio/index.html">Java Image I/O pages</ulink> for a suitable plugin.</para></section>

</chapter><chapter><title>Using GroIMP</title>

<section><title>User Interface</title>
<para>
	GroIMP is equipped with a modern,
	configurable graphical user interface. It supports user-defined layouts
	of panels, including arrangement of panels in tab groups and floating
	windows. <xref linkend="f-ui"/> shows a typical screenshot with 3D
	view.
      </para>
      <figure id="f-ui"><title>Screenshot of
	  GroIMP</title><graphic format="JPEG" fileref="res/GroIMP.jpg"/></figure><para>You can
	see the <emphasis>panels</emphasis> <guilabel>View</guilabel>,
	<guilabel>Attribute Editor</guilabel>, <guilabel>File
	  Explorer</guilabel>, <guilabel>Text Editor</guilabel>,
	<guilabel>Toolbar</guilabel> and <guilabel>Statusbar</guilabel>. The
	panels <guilabel>Images</guilabel> and <guilabel>Materials</guilabel>
	are hidden, they are arranged together with <guilabel>File
	  Explorer</guilabel> in a <emphasis>tab group</emphasis>. The panel
	<guilabel>Text Editor</guilabel> is not contained in GroIMP's main
	window but in its own <emphasis>floating window</emphasis>. Details of
	these panels will be described in the following.</para></section>
    <section><title>Common Panel Handling</title><para>GroIMP's user interface
	consists of an arrangement of panels, e.g., a 3D view or a text
	editor. This arrangement can be changed by the user by Drag&amp;Drop:
	For panels with title bars or panels in a tab group, a Drag&amp;Drop
	operation is performed by dragging  title bars with the mouse. A
	contour indicates where the panel will be dropped if you release the
	mouse button. For panels without title bars (e.g., toolbars,
	statusbars), just drag the panels themselves.</para><para>Every panel
	has a panel menu which provides at least the operations
	<guimenuitem>Undock</guimenuitem> and
	<guimenuitem>Close</guimenuitem>. A panel menu is opened by clicking on
	the title bar of the panel or, if there is no title bar, on the panel
	itself (usually with the right mouse button). The
	<guimenuitem>Undock</guimenuitem> operation undocks the panel out of
	its current location and brings it up in a new floating window, the
	<guimenuitem>Close</guimenuitem> operation closes a
	panel.</para><para>Normally, not all possible panels are actually
	present in the user interface. However, all panels are accessible
	through the <guimenu>Panels</guimenu> menu of GroIMP's main window. If
	a panel you need is missing, just select it in the main
	<guimenu>Panels</guimenu> menu. This brings up the panel in a new
	floating window.</para><para>The arrangement of all panels is called a
	panel <emphasis>layout</emphasis>. The menu <guimenu>Panels/Set
Layout</guimenu> provides a set of predefined layouts which are useful for
distinct tasks; the menu item <guimenuitem>Panels/Add Layout</guimenuitem> adds
the current layout to the list of user-defined layouts of the current
project. User-defined layouts are also accessible in the menu
<guimenu>Panels/Set Layout</guimenu>.</para></section>

<section><title>GroIMP's Projects</title>

<para>The main entity you work on in
	GroIMP is the <emphasis>project</emphasis>. A project may consist of
	various parts, e.g., files, source code, a scene (2D, 3D, or other),
	resource objects like data sets, 3D materials or the like. Several
	projects can be open at the same time, each in its own main
	window.</para><para>You create a new project by choosing the menu item
	<guimenuitem>File/New/Project</guimenuitem>. Via
	<guimenuitem>File/Open</guimenuitem>, projects can be read from a
	file. Different file formats are available: GS and GSZ are GroIMP's
	native project formats, the other formats are imported into a new
	project.</para><para>Saving of a project is done in the
	<guimenu>File</guimenu> menu too. Here, only GS and GSZ are available
	as file formats. The GS file format in fact consists of a set of files
	written in the folder containing the GS file:
	<filename>graph.xml</filename> contains the scene graph of the project,
	the folder <filename>META-INF</filename> some meta information about
	the files, and if there are files included in the project, they will be
	written in the folder (or subfolders) too. To avoid conflicts between
	different projects, it is mandatory to use an own folder for each
	project.</para><para>Contrary to the GS file format, the GSZ file
	format only consists of a single file. This file is actually a file in
	the common zip-format with special content: It contains all the files
	which comprise a project in the GS file format in a single zip
	archive. You can use standard zip tools to examine or even modify its
	contents.</para><para>While working with an open project, there is one
difference between projects in GS/GSZ file format: If you modify and save files
(e.g., text files) contained in a GS project, they will be written to your file
system immediately because the GS file format consists of a set of files in
your file system. However, for a GSZ project, these files are written to an
internal storage: Your modifications are persistently saved only when the whole
project is saved. </para></section>

<section><title>Common Panels</title>

<section><title>File Explorer</title>

<para>GroIMP's <guilabel>File Explorer</guilabel> shows all those files of the
project which have an immediate meaning as files to GroIMP. These are source
code files, plain text files, HTML files and the like. Files which are used to
define non-file-like objects (e.g., images, 3D geometry, data sets) are not
shown in the file explorer panel, they are accessible in the panels of the
corresponding object type.</para><figure id="f-fileexplorer"><title>File
Explorer</title><graphic format="PNG"
		  fileref="res/fileexplorer.png"/></figure><para>If the file
explorer is not already shown, open the panel via the <guimenu>Panel</guimenu>
menu. As you will know it from your system's file browser, GroIMP's file
exporer displays files in a tree-like structure. Files may be activated by a
double-click or pressing the <keycap>Enter</keycap> key: On activation, source
code and text files are opened in the text editor, HTML files are shown in
GroIMP's integrated browser. At the moment, files cannot be renamed, moved or
deleted in the file explorer.</para><para>Files which already exist in your
file system can be added to a project via the menu item
<guimenuitem>Object/New/Add File</guimenuitem>. You have the choice to
<emphasis>link</emphasis> or <emphasis>add</emphasis> these files: A linked
file does not become part of the project, the project just references it in
your file systems. Changes to a linked file take effect on the project when
GroIMP (re-)opens the file. In contrast to a linked file, an added file is
copied into the project, thus, after addition, there is no connection between
the original file and the project any more.</para><para>In <xref
	    linkend="f-fileexplorer"/>, a file explorer panel is
shown. <filename>FTree.rgg</filename> is a source code file,
<filename>FTree.txt</filename> a text file which contains some explanations
about the project FTree, and <filename>index.html</filename> is a link
(indicated by the small arrow at the lower left corner of the icon) to an
HTML file.</para></section>

<section><title>Text Editor</title>

<para>GroIMP is equipped with a simple internal text editor. When you activate
a source code or text file entry in the file explorer, it is opened in the text
editor and can be edited. The usual editing operations (Cut&amp;Paste,
Undo/Redo, Save) are available. <xref linkend="f-texteditor"/> shows a
screenshot.</para>

<figure id="f-texteditor"><title>Text Editor</title><graphic format="PNG" fileref="res/texteditor.png"/></figure>

<para>For some file types, additional actions are triggered when a file of that
type is saved. For example, source code is compiled
immediately.</para></section>

<section><title>Text Editor jEdit</title>

<para>If the jEdit-Plugin is installed, the
<ulink url="http://www.jedit.org/">jEdit</ulink> text editor is used
instead of GroIMP's simple internal text editor.
<xref linkend="f-texteditor-jedit"/> shows a screenshot. jEdit
supports syntax highlighting and contains various edit, search,
and print commands. Comprehensive documentation is available via the
<guimenu>Help</guimenu>-menu of jEdit.
</para>

<figure id="f-texteditor-jedit"><title>Text Editor jEdit</title><graphic format="PNG" fileref="res/texteditor_jedit.png"/></figure>

</section>

<section><title>Image Explorer</title>

<para>Every image used within a GroIMP
project, e.g., a colouring texture of a 3D material, is shown in the
<guilabel>Image Explorer</guilabel>. Its structure is similar to the
<guilabel>File Explorer</guilabel>. New images can be added to a project via
the menu <guisubmenu>Object/New</guisubmenu>: Currently, this menu contains
only the item <guimenuitem>From File</guimenuitem> which reads an existing
image file into the project. All file formats which are supported by your
installation of the Java Image I/O Framework are readable, these are at least
Portable Network Graphics (<filename>png</filename>), JPEG and Graphics
Interchange Format (<filename>gif</filename>). If a format you need is not
supported by your installation, see <xref linkend="s-imageio"/>. As for the
File Explorer, you have the choice to link or add image files to the
project.</para><figure id="f-imgmatattr"><title>Image Explorer, Material
Explorer, Attribute Editor</title><graphic format="PNG" fileref="res/imgmatattr.png"/></figure></section>

<section><title>Attribute Editor</title>

<para>Another panel which you will
encounter often is the attribute editor (<xref linkend="f-imgmatattr"/>). It
is used to edit attributes of a variety of objects: User settings of
configuration objects, geometric attributes of scene objects, attributes of
resource objects like 3D materials, and others.</para><para>Each attribute has
a type, and each type brings up specific edit components in the attribute
editor. For example, the radius attribute of circles or spheres is a numeric
attribute and is editable through a simple input field. The orientation of a
cylinder in 3D space is a 3D vector and, thus, it is editable through a set of
three numeric input fields. Very complex attributes like 3D materials consist
of several subattributes, each of which brings up its own edit components in
the attribute editor.</para><para>In <xref linkend="f-imgmatattr"/>, you can
see the attribute editor for a 3D material of type
<structname>Phong</structname>. Such a material has the attributes
<structfield>Channel Input</structfield>, <structfield>Diffuse
Colour</structfield>, <structfield>Transparency</structfield>,
<structfield>Interpolated Transparency</structfield>,
<structfield>Ambient Colour</structfield>,
<structfield>Emissive Colour</structfield>,
<structfield>Specular Colour</structfield> and
<structfield>Shininess</structfield>. The <structname>Phong</structname>
material shown has a <structname>Checkerboard 2D</structname> surface map as
its <structfield>Diffuse Colour</structfield>, the checkerboard itself has the
attributes <structfield>Channel Input</structfield>, <structfield>Colour
1</structfield> and <structfield>Colour 2</structfield>. As
<structfield>Channel Input</structfield>, an
<structname>UV-Transformation</structname> is chosen, its numeric attributes
are editable through the input fields. For angles and other attributes which
represent physical quantities, their units are shown, in the this case
<userinput>deg</userinput> which stands for degrees. As <structfield>Colour
1</structfield>, an RGB colour is chosen, whose values are modified by
sliders.</para><para><structfield>Colour 2</structfield> of the checkerboard
is set to an image map. One could have chosen an RGB colour as for the first
colour, a Checkerboard 2D as for the diffuse colour of the material, a simple
constant colour, or some other valid type for this attribute. In GroIMP, there
are many attributes whose values may be of a set of different types. For all
these attributes, a button is shown in the attribute editor which pops up a
menu to choose the desired type. Once a type has been chosen, the attribute
value is set to this type, and appropriate edit components are created. They
are shown within a minimizable subpanel. To minimize it (and to maximize it
later on), click on its upper border where a small button is displayed. For
example, the subpanel for the RGB components of the Opacity attribute is
minimized in <xref linkend="f-imgmatattr"/>. A double-click on the upper
border maximizes the subpanel and minimizes all other
panels.</para></section>

<section><title>Preferences</title><para>In the
	  <guilabel>Preference</guilabel>s panel, you can configure some
	  options of GroIMP and its plugins, see <xref
	    linkend="f-preferences"/>.</para>
<figure id="f-preferences">
<title>Preferences Panel (Metal Look &amp; Feel)</title>
<graphic format="PNG" fileref="res/preferences.png"/></figure>

<section><title>Options for the Swing User Interface</title>

<para>The group <guilabel>UI Toolkit/Swing UI</guilabel> in the
<guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> panel lets you choose the Look &amp; Feel of
the Swing user interface and whether window decorations (title bar, borders,
etc.) should be provided by Swing or by the native window manager of your
system. The set of available Look &amp; Feels depends on your Java and GroIMP
installations: GroIMP's binary distribution is bundled with the Kunststoff,
Liquid and Tonic Look &amp; Feels, the web page <ulink
url="http://javootoo.l2fprod.com/">Javootoo</ulink> provides a rich set of Look
&amp; Feels together with instructions how to install them. <xref
	      linkend="f-preferences"/> displays Java's default Look &amp;
Feel, Metal.</para><para>If you switch to another Look &amp; Feel in the
Preferences panel, the user interface will be redrawn immediately. However,
changing the window decorations option only takes effect when a new window is
opened. Also, there are Look &amp; Feels which do not support window
decorations.</para></section></section>

<section><title>Other Explorer Panels</title>

<para>Besides files and images, a variety of other object kinds
is displayed within an explorer panel. For example,
<xref linkend="f-imgmatattr"/> shows the <guilabel>Material Explorer</guilabel>
panel. These panels are always similar to the file explorer or the image
explorer: Objects are shown in a hierarchical tree-like layout, and new
objects are created by the <guisubmenu>Object/New</guisubmenu> menu of the
panel. The contents in this menu depend on the explorer: The <guilabel>Image
Explorer</guilabel> reads in images from files, the <guilabel>Material
Explorer</guilabel> allows the creation of new materials of several material
types, etc.</para></section></section></chapter>


	<appendix id="gfdl">
		<title>GNU Free Documentation License</title>
		<literallayout>
Version 1.2, November 2002

Copyright © 2000, 2001, 2002 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307 USA
Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies
of this license document, but changing it is not allowed.
</literallayout>
		<formalpara id="gfdl-0">
			<title>0. PREAMBLE</title>
			<para>The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook, or other functional and useful document "free" in the sense of freedom: to assure everyone the effective freedom to copy and redistribute it, with or without modifying it, either commercially or noncommercially. Secondarily, this License preserves for the author and publisher a way to get credit for their work, while not being considered responsible for modifications made by others.</para>
		</formalpara>
		<para>This License is a kind of "copyleft", which means that derivative works of the document must themselves be free in the same sense. It complements the GNU General Public License, which is a copyleft license designed for free software.</para>
		<para>We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals for free software, because free software needs free documentation: a free program should come with manuals providing the same freedoms that the software does. But this License is not limited to software manuals; it can be used for any textual work, regardless of subject matter or whether it is published as a printed book. We recommend this License principally for works whose purpose is instruction or reference.</para>
		<formalpara id="gfdl-1">
			<title>1. APPLICABILITY AND DEFINITIONS</title>
			<para id="gfdl-doc">This License applies to any manual or other work, in any medium, that contains a notice placed by the copyright holder saying it can be distributed under the terms of this License. Such a notice grants a world-wide, royalty-free license, unlimited in duration, to use that work under the conditions stated herein. The "Document", below, refers to any such manual or work. Any member of the public is a licensee, and is addressed as "you". You accept the license if you copy, modify or distribute the work in a way requiring permission under copyright law.</para>
		</formalpara>
		<para id="gfdl-mod-ver">A "Modified Version" of the Document means any work containing the Document or a portion of it, either copied verbatim, or with modifications and/or translated into another language.</para>
		<para id="gfdl-secnd-sect">A "Secondary Section" is a named appendix or a front-matter section of the Document that deals exclusively with the relationship of the publishers or authors of the Document to the Document's overall subject (or to related matters) and contains nothing that could fall directly within that overall subject. (Thus, if the Document is in part a textbook of mathematics, a Secondary Section may not explain any mathematics.) The relationship could be a matter of historical connection with the subject or with related matters, or of legal, commercial, philosophical, ethical or political position regarding them.</para>
		<para id="gfdl-inv-sect">The "Invariant Sections" are certain Secondary Sections whose titles are designated, as being those of Invariant Sections, in the notice that says that the Document is released under this License. If a section does not fit the above definition of Secondary then it is not allowed to be designated as Invariant. The Document may contain zero Invariant Sections. If the Document does not identify any Invariant Sections then there are none.</para>
		<para id="gfdl-cov-text">The "Cover Texts" are certain short passages of text that are listed, as Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts, in the notice that says that the Document is released under this License. A Front-Cover Text may be at most 5 words, and a Back-Cover Text may be at most 25 words.</para>
		<para id="gfdl-transparent">A "Transparent" copy of the Document means a machine-readable copy, represented in a format whose specification is available to the general public, that is suitable for revising the document straightforwardly with generic text editors or (for images composed of pixels) generic paint programs or (for drawings) some widely available drawing editor, and that is suitable for input to text formatters or for automatic translation to a variety of formats suitable for input to text formatters. A copy made in an otherwise Transparent file format whose markup, or absence of markup, has been arranged to thwart or discourage subsequent modification by readers is not Transparent. An image format is not Transparent if used for any substantial amount of text. A copy that is not "Transparent" is called "Opaque".</para>
		<para>Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include plain ASCII without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input format, SGML or XML using a publicly available DTD, and standard-conforming simple HTML, PostScript or PDF designed for human modification. Examples of transparent image formats include PNG, XCF and JPG. Opaque formats include proprietary formats that can be read and edited only by proprietary word processors, SGML or XML for which the DTD and/or processing tools are not generally available, and the machine-generated HTML, PostScript or PDF produced by some word processors for output purposes only.</para>
		<para id="gfdl-title-page">The "Title Page" means, for a printed book, the title page itself, plus such following pages as are needed to hold, legibly, the material this License requires to appear in the title page. For works in formats which do not have any title page as such, "Title Page" means the text near the most prominent appearance of the work's title, preceding the beginning of the body of the text.</para>
		<para id="gfdl-entitled">A section "Entitled XYZ" means a named subunit of the Document whose title either is precisely XYZ or contains XYZ in parentheses following text that translates XYZ in another language. (Here XYZ stands for a specific section name mentioned below, such as "Acknowledgements", "Dedications", "Endorsements", or "History".) To "Preserve the Title" of such a section when you modify the Document means that it remains a section "Entitled XYZ" according to this definition.</para>
		<para>The Document may include Warranty Disclaimers next to the notice which states that this License applies to the Document. These Warranty Disclaimers are considered to be included by reference in this License, but only as regards disclaiming warranties: any other implication that these Warranty Disclaimers may have is void and has no effect on the meaning of this License.</para>
		<formalpara id="gfdl-2">
			<title>2. VERBATIM COPYING</title>
			<para>You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium, either commercially or noncommercially, provided that this License, the copyright notices, and the license notice saying this License applies to the Document are reproduced in all copies, and that you add no other conditions whatsoever to those of this License. You may not use technical measures to obstruct or control the reading or further copying of the copies you make or distribute. However, you may accept compensation in exchange for copies. If you distribute a large enough number of copies you must also follow the conditions in section 3. </para>
		</formalpara>
		<para>You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated above, and you may publicly display copies.</para>
		<formalpara id="gfdl-3">
			<title>3. COPYING IN QUANTITY</title>
			<para>If you publish printed copies (or copies in media that commonly have printed covers) of the Document, numbering more than 100, and the Document's license notice requires Cover Texts, you must enclose the copies in covers that carry, clearly and legibly, all these Cover Texts: Front-Cover Texts on the front cover, and Back-Cover Texts on the back cover. Both covers must also clearly and legibly identify you as the publisher of these copies. The front cover must present the full title with all words of the title equally prominent and visible. You may add other material on the covers in addition. Copying with changes limited to the covers, as long as they preserve the title of the Document and satisfy these conditions, can be treated as verbatim copying in other respects.</para>
		</formalpara>
		<para>If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to fit legibly, you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit reasonably) on the actual cover, and continue the rest onto adjacent pages.</para>
		<para>If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document numbering more than 100, you must either include a machine-readable Transparent copy along with each Opaque copy, or state in or with each Opaque copy a computer-network location from which the general network-using public has access to download using public-standard network protocols a complete Transparent copy of the Document, free of added material. If you use the latter option, you must take reasonably prudent steps, when you begin distribution of Opaque copies in quantity, to ensure that this Transparent copy will remain thus accessible at the stated location until at least one year after the last time you distribute an Opaque copy (directly or through your agents or retailers) of that edition to the public.</para>
		<para>It is requested, but not required, that you contact the authors of the Document well before redistributing any large number of copies, to give them a chance to provide you with an updated version of the Document.</para>
		<formalpara id="gfdl-4">
			<title>4. MODIFICATIONS</title>
			<para>You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the Document under the conditions of sections 2 and 3 above, provided that you release the Modified Version under precisely this License, with the Modified Version filling the role of the Document, thus licensing distribution and modification of the Modified Version to whoever possesses a copy of it. In addition, you must do these things in the Modified Version:</para>
		</formalpara>
		<orderedlist id="gfdl-modif-cond" numeration="upperalpha">
			<title>GNU FDL Modification Conditions</title>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>Use in the Title Page (and on the covers, if any) a title distinct from that of the Document, and from those of previous versions (which should, if there were any, be listed in the History section of the Document). You may use the same title as a previous version if the original publisher of that version gives permission. </simpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>List on the Title Page, as authors, one or more persons or entities responsible for authorship of the modifications in the Modified Version, together with at least five of the principal authors of the Document (all of its principal authors, if it has fewer than five), unless they release you from this requirement. </simpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>State on the Title page the name of the publisher of the Modified Version, as the publisher.</simpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>Preserve all the copyright notices of the Document. </simpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>Add an appropriate copyright notice for your modifications adjacent to the other copyright notices. </simpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>
					Include, immediately after the copyright notices, a license notice giving the public permission to use the Modified Version under the terms of this License, in the form shown in the 
					<link linkend="gfdl-addendum">Addendum</link>
					below. 
				</simpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>Preserve in that license notice the full lists of Invariant Sections and required Cover Texts given in the Document's license notice.</simpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>Include an unaltered copy of this License. </simpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>Preserve the section Entitled "History", Preserve its Title, and add to it an item stating at least the title, year, new authors, and publisher of the Modified Version as given on the Title Page. If there is no section Entitled "History" in the Document, create one stating the title, year, authors, and publisher of the Document as given on its Title Page, then add an item describing the Modified Version as stated in the previous sentence. </simpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>Preserve the network location, if any, given in the Document for public access to a Transparent copy of the Document, and likewise the network locations given in the Document for previous versions it was based on. These may be placed in the "History" section. You may omit a network location for a work that was published at least four years before the Document itself, or if the original publisher of the version it refers to gives permission. </simpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>For any section Entitled "Acknowledgements" or "Dedications", Preserve the Title of the section, and preserve in the section all the substance and tone of each of the contributor acknowledgements and/or dedications given therein. </simpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>Preserve all the Invariant Sections of the Document, unaltered in their text and in their titles. Section numbers or the equivalent are not considered part of the section titles. </simpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>Delete any section Entitled "Endorsements". Such a section may not be included in the Modified Version. </simpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>Do not retitle any existing section to be Entitled "Endorsements" or to conflict in title with any Invariant Section. </simpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>Preserve any Warranty Disclaimers. </simpara>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections or appendices that qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no material copied from the Document, you may at your option designate some or all of these sections as invariant. To do this, add their titles to the list of Invariant Sections in the Modified Version's license notice. These titles must be distinct from any other section titles.</para>
		<para>You may add a section Entitled "Endorsements", provided it contains nothing but endorsements of your Modified Version by various parties--for example, statements of peer review or that the text has been approved by an organization as the authoritative definition of a standard.</para>
		<para>You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover Text, and a passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the end of the list of Cover Texts in the Modified Version. Only one passage of Front-Cover Text and one of Back-Cover Text may be added by (or through arrangements made by) any one entity. If the Document already includes a cover text for the same cover, previously added by you or by arrangement made by the same entity you are acting on behalf of, you may not add another; but you may replace the old one, on explicit permission from the previous publisher that added the old one.</para>
		<para>The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by this License give permission to use their names for publicity for or to assert or imply endorsement of any Modified Version.</para>
		<formalpara id="gfdl-5">
			<title>5. COMBINING DOCUMENTS</title>
			<para>
				You may combine the Document with other documents released under this License, under the terms defined in 
				<link linkend="gfdl-4">section 4</link>
				above for modified versions, provided that you include in the combination all of the Invariant Sections of all of the original documents, unmodified, and list them all as Invariant Sections of your combined work in its license notice, and that you preserve all their Warranty Disclaimers.
			</para>
		</formalpara>
		<para>The combined work need only contain one copy of this License, and multiple identical Invariant Sections may be replaced with a single copy. If there are multiple Invariant Sections with the same name but different contents, make the title of each such section unique by adding at the end of it, in parentheses, the name of the original author or publisher of that section if known, or else a unique number. Make the same adjustment to the section titles in the list of Invariant Sections in the license notice of the combined work.</para>
		<para>In the combination, you must combine any sections Entitled "History" in the various original documents, forming one section Entitled "History"; likewise combine any sections Entitled "Acknowledgements", and any sections Entitled "Dedications". You must delete all sections Entitled "Endorsements".</para>
		<formalpara id="gfdl-6">
			<title>6. COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS</title>
			<para>You may make a collection consisting of the Document and other documents released under this License, and replace the individual copies of this License in the various documents with a single copy that is included in the collection, provided that you follow the rules of this License for verbatim copying of each of the documents in all other respects.</para>
		</formalpara>
		<para>You may extract a single document from such a collection, and distribute it individually under this License, provided you insert a copy of this License into the extracted document, and follow this License in all other respects regarding verbatim copying of that document.</para>
		<formalpara id="gfdl-7">
			<title>7. AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT WORKS</title>
			<para>A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other separate and independent documents or works, in or on a volume of a storage or distribution medium, is called an "aggregate" if the copyright resulting from the compilation is not used to limit the legal rights of the compilation's users beyond what the individual works permit. When the Document is included in an aggregate, this License does not apply to the other works in the aggregate which are not themselves derivative works of the Document.</para>
		</formalpara>
		<para>If the Cover Text requirement of section 3 is applicable to these copies of the Document, then if the Document is less than one half of the entire aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts may be placed on covers that bracket the Document within the aggregate, or the electronic equivalent of covers if the Document is in electronic form. Otherwise they must appear on printed covers that bracket the whole aggregate.</para>
		<formalpara id="gfdl-8">
			<title>8. TRANSLATION</title>
			<para>Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may distribute translations of the Document under the terms of section 4. Replacing Invariant Sections with translations requires special permission from their copyright holders, but you may include translations of some or all Invariant Sections in addition to the original versions of these Invariant Sections. You may include a translation of this License, and all the license notices in the Document, and any Warranty Disclaimers, provided that you also include the original English version of this License and the original versions of those notices and disclaimers. In case of a disagreement between the translation and the original version of this License or a notice or disclaimer, the original version will prevail.</para>
		</formalpara>
		<para>If a section in the Document is Entitled "Acknowledgements", "Dedications", or "History", the requirement (section 4) to Preserve its Title (section 1) will typically require changing the actual title.</para>
		<formalpara id="gfdl-9">
			<title>9. TERMINATION</title>
			<para>You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the Document except as expressly provided for under this License. Any other attempt to copy, modify, sublicense or distribute the Document is void, and will automatically terminate your rights under this License. However, parties who have received copies, or rights, from you under this License will not have their licenses terminated so long as such parties remain in full compliance.</para>
		</formalpara>
		<formalpara id="gfdl-10">
			<title>10. FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS LICENSE</title>
			<para>The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised versions of the GNU Free Documentation License from time to time. Such new versions will be similar in spirit to the present version, but may differ in detail to address new problems or concerns. See http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/.</para>
		</formalpara>
		<para>Each version of the License is given a distinguishing version number. If the Document specifies that a particular numbered version of this License "or any later version" applies to it, you have the option of following the terms and conditions either of that specified version or of any later version that has been published (not as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation. If the Document does not specify a version number of this License, you may choose any version ever published (not as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation.</para>
		<formalpara id="gfdl-addendum">
			<title>ADDENDUM: How to use this License for your documents</title>
			<para>To use this License in a document you have written, include a copy of the License in the document and put the following copyright and license notices just after the title page:</para>
		</formalpara>
		<blockquote id="copyright-sample">
			<para>Copyright (c) YEAR YOUR NAME. Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU Free Documentation License". </para>
		</blockquote>
		<para>If you have Invariant Sections, Front-Cover Texts and Back-Cover Texts, replace the "with...Texts." line with this:</para>
		<blockquote id="inv-cover-sample">
			<para>with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES, with the Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being LIST. </para>
		</blockquote>
		<para>If you have Invariant Sections without Cover Texts, or some other combination of the three, merge those two alternatives to suit the situation.</para>
		<para>If your document contains nontrivial examples of program code, we recommend releasing these examples in parallel under your choice of free software license, such as the GNU General Public License, to permit their use in free software.</para>
	</appendix>
</book>
