<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book id="groimp-manual">
  <title>3D Plugin Manual</title>

  <bookinfo>
    <title>3D Plugin Manual</title>

    <pubdate>2006</pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2006</year>

      <holder>Lehrstuhl Grafische Systeme, Brandenburgische Technische
      Universität Cottbus</holder>
    </copyright>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter>
    <title>GroIMP's 3D Plugin</title>

    <section>
      <title>Overview</title>

      <para>As GroIMP's primary purpose is the modelling of three-dimensional
      virtual plants, GroIMP's 3D facilities play a prominent role. They are
      made available by the 3D plugin and contain the following
      features:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>3D geometry objects: Spheres, cones and other primitives,
          NURBS curves and various kinds of NURBS surfaces,
          heightfields.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Materials can be assigned to objects to produce a variety of
          shading effects in visualization. Materials are defined using a
          <emphasis>shading network</emphasis>: This establishes a data flow
          through the nodes of the network which finally leads to the visible
          material properties like colour and opacity. Several kinds of nodes
          are available: Image maps, procedural maps, transformations. You can
          freely mix them in the shading network, which gives you great
          flexibility in defining materials.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>An integrated viewer displays the current scene in three
          dimensions. Easy navigation is enabled by navigation buttons;
          objects can be selected in the viewer. Currently, the viewer
          supports a simple wireframe representation on all Systems. An
          OpenGL-based representation is available for Systems where the
          <emphasis>Java Binding for the OpenGL API</emphasis> (<ulink
          url="???">JOGL</ulink>) is installed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>External renders can be used to create a 3D view of higher
          quality. The POV-Ray Plugin provides a scene export to the POV-Ray
          format which makes it possible to use the free ray-tracer POV-Ray as
          an external renderer, see the <ulink
          url="plugin:de.grogra.ext.povray/doc/index.html">POV-Ray
          manual</ulink>. The resulting image is directly shown in GroIMP's 3D
          view.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="s-3d-ui">
      <title>The 3D User Interface</title>

      <para>GroIMP's 3D user interface consists of two panels, see <xref
      linkend="f-3d-panels" />: The <guilabel>View</guilabel> panel displays
      the scene, the toolbar contains buttons for creating objects and
      selecting the current tool.</para>

      <figure id="f-3d-panels">
        <title>GroIMP's 3D Panels</title>

        <graphic fileref="res/panels.png" format="PNG" />
      </figure>

      <para>In the view panel, objects can be selected with the mouse: The
      object currently under the mouse is highlighted, and by clicking with
      the left mouse button, it becomes selected. If there is more than one
      object under the mouse, you can choose the object you want to select by
      clicking with the middle mouse button: This cycles through the list of
      objects under the mouse. Once an object is selected, its attributes are
      shown in the attribute editor where they can be modified.</para>

      <para>The currently selected object can also be modified by 3D tools. In
      <xref linkend="f-3d-panels" />, you can see three arrows which are the
      handles for GroIMP's 3D translation tool. By dragging the arrows with
      the mouse, the object is moved along the arrow direction. If you use the
      middle mouse button for dragging, the movement is in a plane
      perpendicular to the arrow direction.</para>

      <para>Another 3D tool is the rotation tool. It is activated in the
      toolbar by clicking on the rotation icon. As handles, it displays three
      circles which can be dragged to rotate the selected object.</para>

      <para>Navigation in the view panel is possible with the navigation
      buttons in the view panel's wupper right corner or with the mouse. To
      navigate using the buttons, press a button and drag with the mouse while
      keeping the button pressed. To navigate using the mouse only, press the
      <keycap>Shift</keycap> button and drag with the mouse over the view
      panel: The left mouse button rotates the view, the middle mouse button
      moves the viewpoint in the viewing plane, and the right mouse button
      makes a dolly movement along the viewing direction (or a zoom for a view
      camera with parallel projection). The mouse wheel works similarly to the
      right mouse button.</para>

      <para>The <guimenu>Camera</guimenu> menu of GroIMP's 3D view allows the
      selection of different cameras. Some cameras are predefined, among them
      the common orthographic projections. You can add user-defined cameras to
      your project in the <guilabel>Camera Explorer</guilabel> (the menu item
      <guimenuitem>Panels/Object Explorers/3D/Cameras</guimenuitem> brings it
      up); these cameras can be selected as current camera in the
      <guimenu>Camera</guimenu> menu, too. They can be edited through the
      navigation facilities or in the <guilabel>Attribute
      Editor</guilabel>.</para>

      <para>The <guimenu>Render View</guimenu> menu displays the installed
      external renderers. The POV-Ray Plugin defines an interface to the
      external renderer POV-Ray, a free ray-tracer, which can be used to
      render 3D scenes in high quality, see <ulink
      url="plugin:de.grogra.ext.povray/doc/index.html">POV-Ray
      manual</ulink>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="s-ogl-ui">
      <title>The OpenGL-based 3D User Interface</title>

      <para>GroIMP features OpenGL-accelerated display of the scene. The
      OpenGL-based display may be selected if the <emphasis>Java Binding for
      the OpenGL API</emphasis> (<ulink url="???">JOGL</ulink>) is installed.
      The menu <guimenu>View/Display</guimenu> of GroIMP's 3D view brings up
      the selection for the different supported display modes. These
      are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Wireframe (AWT): A wireframe view of the scene. Will run on
          all systems.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>OpenGL: OpenGL-based view. Will run on all systems with OpenGL
          1.1 support. This mode will display colors and simple
          textures.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>OpenGL (Proteus): OpenGL-based view. Requires a OpenGL 2.1
          compatible GPU. This mode will preview the output of the internal
          raytracer Twilight in realtime. It features:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Preview of most materials including procedurally
              calculated shaders using the OpenGL Shading Language
              (GLSL)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Per pixel lighting</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Rendering of shadows</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Preview of Sky-Nodes as background</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Rendering of transparent materials</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Navigation and control is the same for the Wireframe and both
      OpenGL-based modes as explained in <xref linkend="s-3d-ui" />. A
      comparison of all three modes for an example scene is shown in figure
      <xref linkend="f-3d-view-comparison" /></para>

      <figure id="f-3d-view-comparison">
        <title>Comparison of GroIMP's 3D view modes</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="res/3d_view_comp.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <section id="s-ogl-options">
        <title>Options in OpenGL mode</title>

        <para>The OpenGL view can be configured by opening the Option-Dialog
        (<guimenuitem>View/Display/Option/Edit</guimenuitem>) of GroIMP's 3D
        view while OpenGL is selected. The dialog features the following
        options:</para>

        <para><itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>lighting: If enabled the scene will be lit by the
              user-defined light-nodes (only up to 8 lights will be used). If
              disabled the scene will not be lit resulting in flat colored
              surfaces. [This option is not available for OpenGL (Proteus)
              mode]</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Level of Detail: This option defines how "round" 3D
              Primitives appear. A higher value needs more rendering time but
              increases the quality</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Show points: If disabled the 3D primitive "Point" will not
              be displayed. Points are normally used for displaying
              information of the used RGG model or to visualizie lightsources.
              These objects are not part of the physical scene. Hiding points
              helps to preview the scene as seen in results produced by a
              raytracer. Disabled this option may also increase
              performance.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Show Grid: If enabled a grid of lines is displayed at the
              scene's origin. The grid is an orientation helper while
              navigating and modifying the scene.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Grid dimension: This value sets the dimension of the
              displayed grid (in meters).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Grid spacing: This value defines the spacing between grid
              lines. A spacing of 1.0 means every meter a line is
              drawn.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Grid color (red, green, blue): These three values define
              the color of the grid. Each value may be set to a number between
              0.0 and 1.0. If all values are set to 1.0 the lines of the grid
              will be displayed in white.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Show axes of coordinates: If enabled the orientation of
              the coordinate axes is displayed in the lower left corner. The
              axis are color-coded in red, green and blue representing the x-,
              z-, y-Axes respectively.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Show names at axes: If enabled the names of the axes are
              shown the coordinate axes.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Show display size: If enabled the size of the view in
              pixel is rendered at the upper left corner of the view.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Options in OpenGL (Proteus) mode</title>

        <para>OpenGL (Proteus) mode shares the options of OpenGL mode (see
        <xref linkend="s-ogl-options" />). Additionaly the following options
        are available in the Option-Dialog
        (<guimenuitem>View/Display/Option/Edit</guimenuitem>):</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Enable lights: If this option is enabled contribution of all
            light sources in the scene are shown. If disabled a default,
            directional light source replaces all other lights. This option
            may be disabled if a scene features many lights to increase
            performance.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Use physical lighting falloff: If this option is enabled a
            quadratic falloff is used for all lightsources. This approximates
            the pathtracer of Twilight. If disabled no falloff is used which
            approximates the results of the standard raytracer of
            Twilight.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Enable shadows: If enabled shadows will be approximated and
            rendered to the scene. This will decrease performance drastically
            for dynamic scenes and while editing. For static scenes shadows
            will decrease performance only slightly. Disabling this option has
            the same effect as marking all lightsources as shadowless.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Show sky: If enabled the material of Sky-Nodes is rendered
            as the scenes background. If disabled a generic grey-colored
            pattern is shown.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Show diffuse Sky-Light: If enabled the 3D-View uses
            Sky-Nodes as an additional lightsource. For a bright, blue sky the
            scene will be shaded in a bluish color.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Global brightness: This value is used to scale the
            brightness of the rendered image. A low value will darken the
            scene while a higher value will brighten up the displayed
            picture.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Enable tonemapping: If enabled the value for
            Global-brightness is ignored. The image is transformed by the
            specified algorithm</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Tonemapping algorithm: The selected Tonemapping algorithm
            controlls how the lit scene is presented to the user. The default
            value is linear mapping which divides the channels of each pixel
            by the maximum valued channel over all pixels.</para>

            <para>DRR (Dynamic Range Reduction) uses the algorithm descriped
            in the paper "Dynamic Range Reduction Inspired by Photoreceptor
            Physiology" by Erik Reinhard and Kate Devlin (<ulink
            url="http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/TVCG.2005.9">link</ulink>).
            Currently only the default values for <emphasis>m</emphasis>,
            <emphasis>f'</emphasis>, <emphasis>c</emphasis> and
            <emphasis>a</emphasis> are used.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Enable shader antialiasing: Some materials will result in
            hard edges or aliasing-artefacts. If enabled the visual quality of
            materials may be improved resulting in a small performance
            reduction. (This feature is not implemented by most shaders up to
            now)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Expand planes to infinity: If enabled planes will be
            rendered as infinitely large. If disabled a simple square is used
            to represent planes. This feature may not be supported by all
            GPU's so disabling will help to increase compatibility.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Max. depth layers: If set to a value higher than 0
            transparent objects will be rendered. This value defines the
            maximum number of transparent layers that may be used to composite
            the image. A higher value allows to see more transparent objects
            behind other transparent object. Depending on the scenes setting
            (especially on how many transparent objects are positioned behind
            each other) a high value will reduce performance drastically. A
            small value (around 4) is recommended.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>GroIMP's 3D Objects</title>

      <section>
        <title>Primitives</title>

        <para>GroIMP defines the 3D primitive objects sphere, box, cylinder,
        cone, frustum, parallelogram, plane, and text label. They can be moved
        and rotated interactively as explained in <xref
        linkend="s-3d-ui" />.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>NURBS Curves and Surfaces</title>

        <para>NURBS (Non-Uniform Rational B-Splines) are a popular and
        versatile representation of curves and surfaces. GroIMP contains full
        NURBS support, e.g., techniques to construct NURBS surfaces out of a
        set of NURBS curves, including surface skinning, surfaces of
        revolution, extrusion and sweep surfaces. A detailed description of
        these techniques will follow in later versions of this manual. For the
        time being, you can experiment with the surface settings in the
        <guilabel>Attribute Editor</guilabel>. Of course, you have to create a
        surface via <guimenuitem>Objects/NURBS/Surface</guimenuitem> at
        first.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Scene Objects</title>

        <para>The global 3D objects light and sky are contained in GroIMP.
        They can be placed into the scene similarly to primitive objects. In
        the wireframe representation, the sky object is displayed as a sphere;
        its position is irrelevant because it represents a sky sphere at
        infinity. Visual effects cannot be seen in the wireframe
        representation, use POV-Ray to get a ray-traced image which makes use
        of these objects.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
